<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A brief apologie of Thomas Cartwright against all such slaunderous accusations as it pleaseth Mr Sutcliffe in seuerall pamphlettes most iniuriously to loade him with</title>
            <author>Cartwright, Thomas, 1535-1603.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1596</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 48 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 15 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A18072</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 4706</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S118607</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99853814</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99853814</idno>
            <idno type="VID">19212</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A18072)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 19212)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 416:08)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A brief apologie of Thomas Cartwright against all such slaunderous accusations as it pleaseth Mr Sutcliffe in seuerall pamphlettes most iniuriously to loade him with</title>
                  <author>Cartwright, Thomas, 1535-1603.</author>
                  <author>Throckmorton, Job, 1545-1601.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[28] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>R. Schilders],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[Middelburg :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1596.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Place of publication and printer's name from STC.</note>
                  <note>Edited by Job Throckmorton --STC.</note>
                  <note>One of a series of pamphlets issued in the controversy between Sutclife, Cartwright and Throckmorton. This is a response to: Matthew Sutcliffe.  An answere unto a certaine calumnious letter published by M. Job Throkmorton, and entituled, A defence of J. Throkmorton against the slaunders of M. Sutcliffe.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A-C⁴ D² .</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Sutcliffe, Matthew, 1550?-1629. --  Answere unto a certaine calumnious letter published by M. Job Throkmorton, and entituled, A defence of J. Throkmorton against the slaunders of M. Sutcliffe.</term>
               <term>Throckmorton, Job, 1545-1601.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-11</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-11</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-02</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-02</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:19212:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:19212:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A brief Apologie of <hi>THOMAS CARTWRIGHT</hi> againſt all ſuch ſlaunderous accu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſations as it pleaſeth M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Sutcliffe in ſeuerall pamphlettes moſt iniuriouſly to loade him with.</p>
            <q>A righteous man abhorreth lyes: But th'vngodly ſhameth him ſelf and is put to ſilence, <bibl>Pro. 13.5.</bibl>
            </q>
            <p>1596.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:19212:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:19212:2"/>
            <head>To the Reader.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>F thou be deſirous (good Reader) to ſee the right pourtraiture of <hi>Innocency</hi> truely laied foorth vnto thee in her proper lineaments, then reade this diſcourſe which is not long. Beeing thou ſeest thus prouoked as ſhee is, or rather, to ſpeake the trueth, thus violentlie drawne into th'encounter by the wretched aſſaultes of an vnleaue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned mouth, yet marke, I pray thee, howe ſhee caries her ſelfe, and how ſhee comes armed into the fielde, <hi>Patience, Mildneſſe, Trueth, and a good Conſcience.</hi> This is her armour, theſe be her weapons, and with theſe onely ſhee fights, repelling and ſtri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king backe all the bitter dartes that are throwen against her, only with, <hi>The Lord rebuke thee,</hi> and none otherwiſe. Farre vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like to that babling declaimour who left vs this leſſon of olde: <hi>Si quam maledice<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>do voluptate<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> coepiſti, eam malè audien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>do amittes, &amp;c.</hi> That is, <hi>If thou haue taken any pleaſure in ſpeaking that thou ſhouldeſt not: Thou muſt looſe it a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine by hearing that thou wouldeſt not.</hi> Well knewe the defendour, that howſoeuer this might be pleaſing to the fleaſhe, or keepe deſcant with our corruption, yet he that ſayes, <hi>Mihi vindi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cta,</hi> had taught him another leſſon, namely, That it could in no ſorte ſute with the ſinceritie of the Goſpell, to giue check for check, and rebuke for rebuke: And therefore it is that in his whole Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logie he hath not giuen his aduerſarie ſo much as one glaunce of reproche.</p>
            <p>Let this then be thy Paterne (good Reader whoſoeuer thou art) howe to wreastle with thy affections in the like aſſaultes: It is la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentable
<pb facs="tcp:19212:3"/> I co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>feſſe, that ſuch vncleane mouthes as this ſhould thus take their libertie to diſgrace at will. But muze not at it, good Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, it hath bene ſo in all ages and will be ſo ſtill: For ſo long as the Lord giueth Sata<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> leaue to buffet &amp; aſſaile his church, ſo long thou maieſt be aſſured there wil neuer want a <hi>Rabſhakeh,</hi> a <hi>Shimei,</hi> or a <hi>Senacherib</hi> to play their partes. Neuertheleſſe, heerein thou maiest comfort thy ſelfe, if thou marke how and in what ſorte this reviling generation is curbed, as it were, ſnaffeled and restrained by the powerfull and righteous hand of God, that in the middest of their forwardneſſe and boldneſſe to blunder out what they list without bluſhing, they can hardly for their liues blunder out a trueth, as if the Lord in his ſecrete iudgement had purpoſely and apparauntly blaſted their penne with a lying and diſtempered ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit. All which if thou find verefied without all gaineſay and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ception in the writings of M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> D. <hi>Sutcliffe</hi> and others of that haire, and withall if thou ſee theſe men that doo thus headely and deſperatlie laſh on in diſgrace of others, to be them ſelues in their ſeuerall accuſations ſo palpably taken tardie, that the very walles and ſtones of the ſtreetes may convince them of vntrueth: if I ſay thou find this to be true (and for proofe therof I referre thee to this ſhort and modest defence) haue patience in thy ſelfe and giue the glory to God, who doth thus, thou ſeest, in his wiſedome make a way and paſſage for the clearing of th'innocent, euen thorough the mouth and malice of th'accuſer him ſelfe.</p>
            <p>Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cerning ſuch things as it pleaſeth him ſo earneſtly to father vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Mr <hi>Cart.</hi> &amp; others by hereſay &amp; report, I can not but muze that a man of his coate and calling is no more ſmitten &amp; abaſhed at it then he is, For preſuppoſe that one ſhould heare by report that M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Sutcliffe was once taken with falſe dice at <hi>Geneva,</hi> and thervpon being forced to flie the Towne, ſhould euer ſince beare a kind of in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veterate hatred &amp; malice to M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
               <hi>Beza</hi> and th'Elders there: This
<pb facs="tcp:19212:3"/> beeing knowen onely to vs by report (how true ſoeuer the thing might be in it ſelfe) I would faine know for my learning, whether this were <hi>aequalance,</hi> or how it might ſute with any meaſure of indifferency, forthwith without any farther examinatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to ſpread it abroade in print. And yet this you ſhall finde to be an vſuall and ordinarie courſe with M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Deane of <hi>Exeter,</hi> in his ſolemne infor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mations and perſonall pleadinges againſt good men: Marke it who liſt in him, if the caſe concerne anie of theſe <hi>Diſciplinarians,</hi> he is of that good nature &amp; ready witte, that rather then he wil be to ſeeke for matter, he will not ſticke to rake the chanell ſometimes &amp; take whatſoeuer comes next to hand, though it lie all to be troden and tra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pled on in the ſtreetes: yea and of that which I beleeue the pooreſt Scavenger in a towne would be loth to ſtoupe for, he with a little helpe and forbiſhing of M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
               <hi>Surveiour of Diſcipline,</hi> frameth for the most parte ſome irrefragable &amp; tempeſtuous con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluſion against theſe new plot-formers, and then forſooth to the Preſſe it must in all post hast with ſome rhetoricall varniſh of In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>novation: as if <hi>Quidlibet ex quolibet,</hi> or as if the poorest &amp; most patched Record vnder the ſunne (that bluſheth, it may be, to ſee the light) were evidence ſtrong enough against a <hi>Preci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſian.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now there bee that thinke that of all other charges thus ſtrangely and vnwoorthily impoſed vppon this Reuerend man, the charge of ignorance, and that his woorkes ſhould be <hi>a fardle of fooleries,</hi> is the moſt out of ioint and approching neareſt to impudency. But ſure for mine owne parte I doo not thinke ſo, neither doo I ſee why his aduerſarie might not with as great reaſon, yea and euery way with as good a conſcience appeache him of ignoraunce as of diſloyaltie. For allow that our Vni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſities togeather with forreine Nations and Churches may ſufficientlie controll the Reporter in the one, yet this letteth not but that the Countries and places of the Mans reſiance,
<pb facs="tcp:19212:4"/> can, for neede, giue as plentifull testimonie in th'other. And therefore why a man of that eaſie gift and rolling veine, ſo ſlip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per in the ſeare as Maister <hi>Sutcliffe</hi> is, ſhould make it more dain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie to ſpare M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
               <hi>Cart.</hi> in his learning then he doeth in his loialty (hauing the like warrant and authoritie for both) I ſee neither reaſon nor ſenſe. The best is, thou hast heere by this meanes (good Reader) (in th'euenneſſe and equabilitie of the Dostors hande to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards this man) an vnfallible line laied before thee, whereby thou mayest meaſure all the rest of his reproches ſo vnconſciona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blie throwen vpon others. For hath he dealt truely, modestly, cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritably, and chriſtianly with this man? Then make thou no doubt or question but he hath afoorded full as good meaſure to o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers. On the contrarie, hath he made no bones hande ouer heade and that beyonde all compaſſe of chriſtianitie to ſpeake his pleaſure of this man, beeing a man ſo notably graced in giftes, and one that hath ſo many vncontrollable euidences of his wiſe and dueti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full cariage of himſelfe? If he haue done this (as the reading of this Apologie will make it cleare vnto thee) Then what reaſon haſt thou to maruell or thinke ſtraunge if thou ſee him nowe and then moſt fowly and ſhamefully ouer-reache him ſelfe against o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers that are farre ſhort of this man in iudgement and ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>encie?</p>
            <p>It is written of <hi>Socrates,</hi> that beeing vniustly put to death without cauſe: while he was going to execution, his wife followed him aloofe of howling and weeping and crying aloude: <hi>O my huſband dieth guiltles, dieth guiltleſſe.</hi> Wherevnto the good old man (looking backe vpon her with a frowning &amp; angry coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance) replied thus: <hi>Why, thou fooliſh woman, wouldeſt thou haue me dye guiltie?</hi> This being the ſpeach of a heathen man, voied of the true knowledge of God, will riſe vp, I feare, in iudgement againſt many of vs that profeſſe chriſtianitie in this age, whoſe common corruption is ſuch, that when we are wrong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully
<pb facs="tcp:19212:4"/> burdened with any matter of diſgrace, we frette at nothing more then that the thing is falſe that is ſo charged vppon our heades. <hi>Why, if I were guiltie</hi> (ſayeth one) <hi>or if it were true that they report of me, it would neuer grieue me:</hi> wheras in trueth (if we did rightlie conſider of it) it ſhould grieue vs and humble vs most to be guiltie, or that thoſe things ſhould bee true that are thus blowen abroad againſt vs. Wilt thou knowe then (good Reader) howe to cary thy ſelfe when thou art thus iniuri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſlie dealt with by any falſe charge or impoſition? Looke vppon th'example of the holy Saintes and ſeruants of God in the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, and as thou ſeeſt them doo, ſo doo thou. <hi>Anna</hi> when ſhee was charged by <hi>Eli</hi> to be druncken, did not frette or ſnuffe at it, or looke vpon the man with a diſdainfull eye, but in much patience and modeſtie made aunſweres <hi>Nay, my Lord, not ſo,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Sam. 1.15.16.</note> 
               <hi>I haue drunke neither wyne nor ſtrong drinke, but haue pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red forth my ſoule before the Lord, count not thy hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mayde a wicked woman, for of th'aboundance of my griefe haue I ſpoken, &amp;c.</hi> Saint <hi>Paul</hi> likewiſe, when hee was charged by <hi>Feſtus,</hi> to be beſides him ſelfe, was, we ſee, no whit diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempered or inflamed with it, but made anſwere in all wiſedome and reuerence: <hi>I am not madd, moſt noble Feſtus,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Act. 26.25</note> 
               <hi>but I ſpeake the wordes of trueth and ſoberneſſe, &amp;c.</hi> This then muſt be thy courſe (good Reader) and theſe be the ſteppes that thou muſt treade in. Thou knoweſt whoſe counſell and admoniſhment it is, <hi>not to ſuffer as a malefactour:</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Pet. 4.15</note> Looke thou to that then in anie caſe.</p>
            <q>
               <l>Hic murus aheneus eſto</l>
               <l>Nil conſcire ſibi, nulla palleſcere culpa.</l>
            </q>
            <p>Keepe thou ſtill a good conſcience, and let the cleareneſſe of thy heart, and innocency of thy hands be as a wall of braſſe vnto thee, and leaue the reſt to the Lorde, to doo what ſeemeth good in his
<pb facs="tcp:19212:5"/> owne eies, And then if Satan doo rage, or his instrumentes doo re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vell or revile neuer ſo much, tearming thee a drunkard, a madd man, a Traitour, a Conſpirator, an Innovatour, or what they will els, be not thou troubled or diſmaied with it, but rather reioice and giue God thankes. For if thou be able truely to ſay with th'Apoſtle in the teſtimony of thine owne hart, <hi>By honour and diſhonor, By good report and euill report,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 Cor. 6.8.</note> 
               <hi>as deceyuers and yet true, &amp;c.</hi> Then (howſoeuer the bloudthirſtie may gnaſhe and grind their teeth at thee) thy conſcience may be at peace: and thou maieſt chearefully anſwere thy good friendes (that are peradven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture agrieued to ſee the falſehoode and indignity of th'impoſitions laied vppon thee) as <hi>Socrates</hi> did to his wife, <hi>Why my Mai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters would you haue me ſuffer guilty, or be ſlaundered and ill ſpoken of deſervedly?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thus dooing what knowest thou, whether the Lord (who hath the hartes of all men in his handes) will make thy condemners to be thy clearers, and thy enemies thy friends, yea and turne all this ſtorme and tempest of vntruthes to thy farther peace, clearing, &amp; ſecuritie in th'end? For was there euer a more bitter and malici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous enemy then <hi>Saul</hi> was to <hi>Dauid?</hi> And yet we ſee how the Lord forced this wretched man (after many falſe ſurmiſes and vniust ielouſies of treaſon and conſpiracy againſt him) to pronounce ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence for <hi>Dauids</hi> acquitall in theſe woordes:<note place="margin">1 Sam. 24.17.</note> 
               <hi>Thou art more righteous then I.</hi> And who knowes whether the Lorde may woorke the like effecte and remorſe in M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
               <hi>Sutcliffe</hi> ere hee die, euen to force him in like maner (after all his bundle of outcryes and vniuſt accuſations) to paſſe the white ſtone on the behalfe of th'accuſed, and him ſelfe to pronounce: <hi>That certeinly Tho. Cart.</hi> &amp; <hi>Steph. Egerto<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> are much more righteous the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he,</hi> and therevppon to adde farther as the ſame <hi>Saul</hi> did afterward, <hi>I haue ſinned,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Sam. 26.21.</note> 
               <hi>I haue played the foole, I haue erred ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedingly,</hi> in ſlaundering and belying th'innocent. Sure I am,
<pb facs="tcp:19212:5"/> it were happie and thrice happy for him if he might liue to doe this of conſcience. But whether he doo or no, labour thou alwayes (good Reader) ſo to walke as thou maieſt not iustly bee touched, with anie thing that may be a ſtaine to thy holy profeſsion. And ſo harbouring ſtill in thy breaſt the comfortable gueſt of a good conſcience (as an aſſwagement of all the miſeries and diſcontent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentes of this life) ceaſe not to pray in the ſpirit for the peace of Ieruſalem, and for her right excellent Maieſtie that hath bene ſo long Gods good inſtrument of that happie peace, That as <hi>Ioſua</hi> commaunded the ſunne to ſtand till he were avenged on his eni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, So the Lord would commaund this Sunne-ſhine of our peace to ſtand and neuer to goe downe, till all the Enemies of his church be brought low to the duſt. And as that was the longeſt day that e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer was, ſo this (hauing bene already by the mercy of God the hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pieſt) may alſo prooue by the power of God to be the longeſt raigne that euer was: That the date of her life may (if it pleaſe the Lord) and with the laſt date and diſſolution of this earth, to the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuall bliſſe and renown of this Land, to the terror &amp; amazing of the wicked, to the comfort and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioycing of the godly, and to her owne euerlaſting peace and hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pines in the life to come.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:19212:6"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:19212:6"/>
            <head>
               <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g> A brief of <hi>Thomas Cartwright</hi> to the printed ſlau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ders of M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> D. Sut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cliffe, Deane of <hi>Exeter,</hi> ſo farre as they concerne the ſame <hi>Tho. Cartwright.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>HIs ſlaunders are either in breach of neceſſarie due<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties impoſed vppon all Chriſtians: or in thinges which, in their nature being indifferent, are by him (in reſpect of mine eſtate) giuen out as things of no good report.</p>
            <div type="accusation">
               <head>M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> D. Sutcliffes charge.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>In the former kinde is his charge of</hi> Conſpiracie with <hi>Hacket</hi> and <hi>Copinger</hi> to a mutuall communication with <hi>Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinger</hi> by woord, writing and conſenting, Fol. 10. p. 2. and fol. 44 p. 2. And that he did not diſſwade him, but rather willed him that he ſhould attempt nothing but by adviſe, and that he ſhould bee wiſe and circumſpect: <hi>which woordes he ſetteth downe in a diuers letter from the letter of his own booke: as if they were woordes of a letter of</hi> Thomas Cartwrightes <hi>to</hi> Copin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, fol. 48. p. 2.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="answer">
               <head>T'hanſwere of Thomas Cartwright.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Hacket</hi> was a man whom, to my knowledge, I neuer ſaw: ſo was <hi>Arthington,</hi> vntill he was freed of his priſon he en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dured for his miſdemeanor: with <hi>Copinger</hi> I had acquain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance vpon occaſion of M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
                  <hi>Ambroſe Copinger,</hi> chief officer to the right Honorable, th'Earle of <hi>Warwike;</hi> For, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ming to his houſe neceſſarily for the ſetling of th'eſtate of th'<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>Hoſpital of the right Honorable th'Earle of <hi>Leicester:</hi>
                  <pb facs="tcp:19212:7"/> there I mette with this <hi>Copinger</hi> ſundry times ſome three or foure yeares before his lewed practiſe brake foorth: with the former two I had neuer conference either by Letter or otherwiſe by meſſage ſent from them to me, or from me to them. Betweene <hi>Copinger</hi> and me touching this matter I am charged with, this onely paſſed which followeth: Whileſt I was in priſon in the Fleere, M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
                  <hi>Rafe Hockenhull</hi> propounded vnto me, as things he deſired to be reſolued of in the behaulf of one of his acquaintance, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> whether there were anie Apoſtles, Prophetes and Euan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geliſtes in theſe daies, I anſwered that thoſe callings cea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed many hundred yeares agoe, and as no Apoſtles were euer hereafter to be looked for, ſo th'other two were not to be expected vnleſſe God in th'vtter waſte and deſola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Church did extraordinarily raiſe them vp for th'erection of a church out of the duſt: And therefore that there was no vſe of ſuch men amongſt vs. To a ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond queſtion, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> how and by what markes ſuch a one as thought him ſelf one of theſe, might in deed know whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther he were ſo or not, I anſwered that this doubting of the matter, was an evident and an invincible argument that he was none: For that ſuch as haue a calling imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diatly from God, are not to aſke counſell of fleaſh and bloud; as thoſe which haue th'vnboubted teſtimony of Gods ſpirit vnto their ſpirites that they are called of him. Wherevpon M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
                  <hi>Hockenhull</hi> telling me that it was <hi>Copinger</hi> which had entred into ſuch conceite of him ſelfe: I deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red him to deale with him for diſwading him from ſuch frantike opinions, which he told me he did accordingly. And afterwardes, ſome while before his lewed practiſe brake foorth, he admoniſhed ſome of his kindred before <hi>Copinger</hi> him ſelfe, that if he belonged to him, he that day
<pb facs="tcp:19212:7"/> before the morrow would make him faſt either in Brid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>well or Bedlem. After ſome ſpace of the demaund of theſe queſtions, he ſent by M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
                  <hi>Hockenhull</hi> to entreate that he might come to me into the Fleete: For that if he might ſo doe, he did not doubt but he would ſhew me ſuch evident tokens of an extraordinarie callinge, as I ſhould haue no power to deny it, and that he would for further ſecuritie in this matter, come wayting vpon M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
                  <hi>Hockenhull</hi> in a blewe coate. To whom I returned this an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwere, that if he came to me, I would not once ſo much as ſpeake with him: For that his diſeaſe was of that kinde as needed ſome other remedie then diſputation. And if he deſired to be reſolued of the trueth in that matter, there were other both for their learning &amp; libertie more fitte to deale with him then I was. Not long after this, the ſame M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
                  <hi>Hockenhull</hi> tolde me that becauſe <hi>Copinger</hi> might not come vnto me, he had written me a letter, which he had ſent by him, to whom I ſaied, I would re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue none from him, and ſo returned his letter without ſo much as once taking it into my hand or looking vpon the ſuperſcription: Whereby may appeare how vntrue it is that I and <hi>Copinger</hi> had mutuall conference by word and letters, to whom (in my knowledge) I neuer wrote in my life: aſſured I am, neuer ſince he entred into this wretched practiſe. After this I heard of M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
                  <hi>Hockenhull,</hi> that <hi>Copinger</hi> would informe her Maieſtie of certeine horrible treaſons committed by perſonages of high cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling, both in Church and common wealth: which as I alwaies eſteemed vaine, knowing the broken witte of the man, ſo, when by report I vnderſtoode the particulers thereof (which argued one bereaued of common ſenſe) I deſired old M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
                  <hi>Michil</hi> that if <hi>Copinger</hi> came to the right
<pb facs="tcp:19212:8"/> Honorable my very good Ladie the Counteſſe of <hi>War<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wicke</hi> for her mediation vnto her excellent Maieſtie for ſuch matters as he would deliuer: He would ſignifie that, although I knew her wiſedome otherwiſe able eaſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie without anie writing to ſound his folly, yet that it would pleaſe her to take this notice of me (which other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe ſhe might be ignoraunt of) that he was ouertaken with ſtraunge conceites of ſome extraordinarie calling and giftes he was fartheſt from. Againe this whole mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of <hi>Hackets Conſpiracie,</hi> being by commiſſion to certeine of her Maieſties moſt honorable Counſel and other wiſe and graue men commended to be examined: I leaue it to be conſidered whether M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> D. <hi>Sutcliffe</hi> bee ſo quicke ſighted as by him ſelfe and his Inquiſitours, hauing (for anie thing I can learne) but the ſame groundes her Maie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſties Commiſſioners had, to finde out that which men of ſo great wiſedome and circumſpection, with ſo great meanes as they had of commaundement ouer all that might bring anie light vnto that matter, could not finde out: And whether this dealing of his bee not ſome charge of want in them either of wiſedome in not fin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding it out, or of fidelitie in not once calling me to th'an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwere of it. Moreouer, <hi>Arthington</hi> being compacte in this conſpiracie with <hi>Hacket</hi> and <hi>Copinger,</hi> if there were a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie hande of mine in that wretched practiſe, in all likeli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hoode <hi>Arthington</hi> muſt needes be priuie vnto it: he is a man aliue let him be examined, and a man alſo whom I neuer ſpake too, nor cauſed to be ſpoken with in my life. His reaſons to induce his reader to thinke his accuſations to be true are (ſo farre as I remember) theſe: The firſt is touching our mutuall conference by letters, which is al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>readie aunſwered: Another, my concurrance wtih <hi>Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinger</hi>
                  <pb facs="tcp:19212:8"/> in faſting. I confeſſe that, as there was iuſt cauſe of humbling my ſelf in faſting, in feeling the diſpleaſure of her excellent Maieſtie and others in great authoritie vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der her, ſo did I ſometimes beſtowe my ſelfe in that exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe. But that I did it the ſame day that <hi>Copinger</hi> and his complices, or at the leaſt with anie notice either giuen to him of my faſting, or receiued from him of his faſting, I vtterly denie as a thing moſt vntrue. A third reaſon is, that <hi>Hacket</hi> and his fellowes commended me at the croſſe in Cheape aboue the writers of our age: I acknowledge their great follie in that commendation or madneſſe ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, who am ſcarce woorthie to beare the bookes after many that haue liued, and yet doo liue in this age, yea &amp; in this Church of our lande. But M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> D. <hi>Sut.</hi> report here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in is not vpright, for although I was not preſent, yet I heard of diuers (and therein referre my ſelfe to the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membrance of thoſe that were ſtanders by) that their ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſiue praiſe was of <hi>Thomas Cortwright,</hi> that had bene ſometimes when he firſt wrote in the cauſe of the Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pline of the Church, but not of him as he now was, for that (as was ſaied) he was faine away from his former loue. Laſtly, that M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
                  <hi>Cartwright</hi> (ſaieth he) <hi>was a medler in thoſe matters and well vnderſtood them, it appeareth by a letter of</hi> Io. Bowmans <hi>(ſeruant in Oundle) to</hi> Wigginton: <hi>I deſire you</hi> (ſaieth he) <hi>to ſend me the copye of a writing which you had from M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>
                  </hi> Cartwright <hi>vpon the Court matters, when goodman</hi> Hacket <hi>was with you the first time.</hi> M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Wigginton, I am aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſured, neuer receiued from me any writing during the time of my impriſonment or afterwardes, or at any time of my life, to my beſt remembrance, whereof let M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
                  <hi>Wig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginton</hi> that liueth be examined. But if he had receiued a writing of the court matters in the ſtarre Chamber, how
<pb facs="tcp:19212:9"/> thereof it can be co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cluded that I was a medler in this mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, let all men iudge, for my part I vnderſtand no ſequell of it, vpon all which both witneſſes and reaſons I leaue it to be iudged, how vntrue it is that M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> D. <hi>Sutcliffe</hi> dooth charge me with touching the matter of <hi>Hacket</hi> and <hi>Copin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, &amp;c.</hi> both in wordes, writing and conſent, which ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer ſpake with them of it in my life, neuer wrote vnto them, nor receiued writing or meſſage fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> them further then I my ſelf haue confeſſed: whereof let it alſo be fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther iudged whether I was conſenting to that wretched practiſe.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="accusation">
               <head>
                  <hi>M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> D.</hi> Sutcliffes accuſation fol. 13. p. 1.</head>
               <p>Yea and <hi>Thomas Cartwright</hi> (they ſay) dooth woorke ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traordinary miracles: And fol. 58. p. 2. A legend of M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Cart<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wright his miracles, which paſſeth from hand to hand and is much esteemed amongst the brethre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> is promiſed to come forth.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="answer">
               <head>Th'anſwere of Tho. Cartwright.</head>
               <p>Being (as I feele my ſelf) ſhort of th'ordinary works of my calling both in generall duties of chriſtianitie, and in the particuler way of the gouernement of mine owne fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>milie: woe ſhould be vnto me if I ſhould vainly boaſt of miraculous works, which my ſelf haue eſpecially written againſt, in condemning extraordinary callings whereof miracles are the ſeales: yet M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> D. <hi>Sutcliffe</hi> ſeemeth to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſinuate thus much (I ſay inſinuate) for that the brethren he brandeth to haue them in eſtimation (I doubt not) he meaneth to be men ſo fauouring me as they would bee loth to doo it if they thought it would not ſtande with my good liking. Now let the towne wherein I dwell be examined, whether any voice te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ding herevnto did euer
<pb facs="tcp:19212:9"/> come from me. And, as I thinke, none can be produced that will glory in this follie: ſo my deſire is, that when this <hi>Legend</hi> ſhall come forth, there may be for the credite of him that ſetteth it out, the names of the reporters, &amp; likewiſe of the brethre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> layed downe that are guiltie of the dotage he ſpeaketh of, that thereby they may be cleared, or otherwiſe paſſe co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>demnation of the follie he chargeth them with.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="accusation">
               <head>
                  <hi>M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> D.</hi> Sutcliffes accuſation, fol. 45. p. 2.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Thomas Cartwright</hi> examined in the ſtarre Chamber vpon certeyne poyntes of her Maiesties Supremacie, refu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to anſwere, and pleaded that he was not bound.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="answer">
               <head>Thomas Cartwrightes <hi>anſwere.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>I refuſed it as eſteeming it impertinent vnto that cauſe, not otherwiſe, vnto which afterward, vpon commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment I gaue anſwere in writing vnto her Maieſties moſt honorable Counſell. And to her Maieſties ſupremacie I haue bene ſworne (at the leaſt) fiue or ſixe times, and if there be doubt of any change of my iudgement, I am ready to take th'oth againe.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="accusation">
               <head>M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> D. Sutcliffes <hi>accuſation.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <hi>M. Cartwright</hi> highly commendeth <hi>Fenners</hi> booke, which giueth authoritie to ſuperior perſons to restraine their Soue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raigne, as th'Ephori in Sparta.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="answer">
               <head>Thomas Cartwrightes <hi>anſwere.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>I take it M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
                  <hi>Fenner</hi> giueth no ſuch authoritie, but only where the lawes of the lande doo eſtabliſh ſuch an autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie
<pb facs="tcp:19212:10"/> as the <hi>Ephori</hi> in <hi>Lacedaemonia</hi> had. And if M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
                  <hi>Fenner</hi> did, yet how doth my Epiſtle commendatorie ſet before his booke make me of his iudgement, as if he that co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth a book iuſtifieth what ſoeuer is in the booke, or as if, notwithſtanding M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
                  <hi>Fenners</hi> ſingular learning (which for his age many, I doubt not, both at home and abroade doo eſteeme) I might not or doo not differ from him in ſome things conteined in his booke: beſides he him ſelfe confeſſing, that by oth in the ſtarre Chamber I haue diſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vowed th'alowance of any ſuch opinion which he fathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth of M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
                  <hi>Fenner,</hi> let it be conſidered with what minde he ſo often rubbeth vppon this point. And both for this and the former charge, I leaue it to bee conſidered with what chriſtian modeſtie M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
                  <hi>Sutcliffe</hi> may now the ſecond and the third time (and that in print) mooue queſtion of thoſe thinges to our diſcredite, which her Maieſties moſt honorable Counſell was pleaſed, ſhould be no further proceeded in, and that he is not contented with that im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſonment we endured, which their Honors are ſatisfied with. Laſtly, my iudgement in ſundry matters of the Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipline excepted, wherein differing from ſundry learned men in our Church, I haue the conſent of many worthie Churches and godly learned both of this and other ages, I would bee aſhamed for that ſingular mercy God hath ſhewed me by her Maieſties moſt gratious gouuernment to come behinde M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
                  <hi>Sutcliffe</hi> in anie duetie that my poore hand is able to reach vnto. And that he dareth me not once but ſundry times to anſwere touching theſe matters of Diſcipline, I think it not ſo fitte for me to vndertake it, there being ſo many better able therevnto then I, eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>allie in this declyning &amp; forgetfull age of mine. And yet if my anſwere might haue either that alowance of print,
<pb facs="tcp:19212:10"/> or paſſage that his hath, and none other were found: I my ſelf in this weakneſſe I am in, would not be behind with anſwere to anie thing that he hath bene able to alleadge in this behalfe: If there be any thing in his writings, the anſwere wherof is not already ſet downe by ſuch as haue written in that cauſe: And that my ſilence in the cauſe of Diſcipline is not altogeather either of th'inhabilitie or feare, M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> D. <hi>Sutcliffe</hi> would ſo willingly faſten, or rather force vpon me, let this be for an Argument, that where I was ſet on worke by the right honorable Sir <hi>Francis Wal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſingham</hi> for th'aunſwere of th'annotations of the Ieſuites vpon the new teſtament, &amp; had traueled therin to a rude and firſt draught of a great part thereof: vnderſtanding from ſome in authoritie that I might not deale with it, I did not onely not ſet any thing out my ſelfe, but alſo ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſtly laboured by letters and friendes heere and in Scot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land both the<note n="(a)" place="margin">And if he ſtayed the pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhing of that wherevnto he was once alo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wed by autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie, it is not in al likelihood to be thought that he would haſtely publiſh anie thing of him ſelf, how ſoeuer he migt be perſwaded of the truth of it?</note> hinderaunce of printing ſome partes therof, which beeing brought to Sir <hi>Francis</hi> afterwarde (much againſt my will) came into the handes of diuers to whom I would neuer haue let them come.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="accusation">
               <head>M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> D. Sutcliffes accuſation.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Cartwright</hi> vpon the comming forth of <hi>Martin</hi> is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ported to haue ſaied that it was no matter, if the BB. were ſo handled, ſeeing they would take no warning. fol. 48. p. 1.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="answer">
               <head>Thomas Cartwrightes <hi>anſwere.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>Let it be iudged what chriſtian loue it is to committe ſuch things to print vpon a bare report. And if the repor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters had bene named as in other caſes where he doth call out the perſons by their names, the trueth might haue
<pb facs="tcp:19212:11"/> the better appeared: For me, I am able to produce wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes, that the firſt time that euer I heard of <hi>Martin Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prelate,</hi> I teſtified my great miſliking &amp; grief, for ſo naugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, and ſo diſorderly a courſe as that was. And therefore where fol. 51. pa. 1. he aſketh when I will condemne th'<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vnlawfull and vnciuill practiſe of <hi>Martin</hi> and <hi>Penry?</hi> I aſke againe what office or charge I haue to publiſhe con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demnation vpon euery vnlawfull and vnciuill writing that cometh abroad? And yet I haue witneſſes, that euen publikely when I was alowed to preach, I condemned all dealing in that kinde.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="accusation">
               <head>
                  <hi>M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> D.</hi> Sutcliffes accuſation, fol. 61. p. 1.</head>
               <p>Extemporall prayers <hi>Tho. Cartwright</hi> commendeth most highly, as being vttered by the holy Ghostes ſecret inſpira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion: and ſcarſe would be induced (when time was) to like of a preſcript forme of prayer. <hi>And in the margen is ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded,</hi> Thomas Cartwrightes reply.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="answer">
               <head>Thomas Cartwrightes onſwere.</head>
               <p>Where, in my replie, or in treatiſe of what matter I re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member not, nor M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
                  <hi>Sutcliffe</hi> (I beleeue) ſhall euer ſhew that <hi>Thomas Cartwright</hi> hath ſo litle knowledge of diuini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie as to affirme that the extemporall prayers of anie (how able ſoeuer in theſe daies) are vttered by the holy ghoſtes ſecret inſpiratio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. And in what place or time and in whoſe hearing could I ſcarcely be induced to like of a preſcript forme of praier? The noting of theſe circu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſtances, which he doth diligently, yea curiouſly (where he thinketh they may ſerue the turne) would eaſely haue bewraied, th'vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trueth hereof. My co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tinuall practiſe in the miniſterie wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſeth againſt it, for in the ſpace of fiue yeres I preached
<pb facs="tcp:19212:11"/> at <hi>Antwerpe</hi> and <hi>Middelborogh,</hi> I did euery ſunday read the praier out of the booke: And all the while I preached at <hi>Warwike</hi> there were few ſermons I euer made there but (to my remembrance) I did ſhutt vp the praier either be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore or after the ſermon with the Lordes praier: Beſides that the praier before the ſermon ordinarily was a ſet and accuſtomed forme of praier howſoeuer I read it not out of the booke, and likewiſe was that after the ſermon ſome ſmall part excepted, where in my praier I applied ſome principal pointes of the doctrine the handled: All which I would not haue done, if I had not alowed, yea well li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked alſo a preſcript forme of praier. And hitherto of the former kind of ſlaunders concerning the breach of neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſarie dueties impoſed vpon all chriſtians. The ſecond of things indifferent in their owne nature foloweth: For as touching his charge of odious and ignorant railing, &amp;c. I referre my ſelf to indifferent iudgeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t vpon the bookes which are extant.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="accusation">
               <head>
                  <hi>M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> D. Sutcliffes</hi> accuſation in his former booke, th'effect whereof is.</head>
               <p>That notwithſtanding <hi>Thomas Cartwright</hi> condemneth Executorſhip in other Ministers of the woord, yet that he was content to be Executor to his brother <hi>Stubbes</hi> his will: Looke alſo fol. 69. pag. 2. of his laſt booke.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="answer">
               <head>Thomas Cartwrightes <hi>anſwere.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>I was not ſo much as named in my brothers will, and to put of M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
                  <hi>Sutcliffes</hi> ſhift of anſwere he hath made to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſe him ſelf in his latter booke, that by the woord of laſt will he would vnderſtand anie conveiance lately made
<pb facs="tcp:19212:12"/> before his death, wherein truſt was committed vnto me: I anſwere, that my brother <hi>Stubbes</hi> did neuer either long before or ſoone after his death put me in truſt with anie of his worldly eſtate either by woord or writing. Neither is there (as M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
                  <hi>Sutcliffe</hi> ſurmiſeth) any vnkindneſſe <hi>of my Brothers towardes me,</hi> in not putting me in truſt which would not that way be employed, or my vnkindneſſe to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards him, who truſted him with my whole eſtate that way. And that my <hi>Brothers wife and kindred rested not ſatiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied with my dealing:</hi> either is an vntrueth of M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
                  <hi>Sutcliffes</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port, or a moſt cauſeleſſe complaint of their behaulf. For where in regard of my wifes portion of twoo hundred pound, I had an annuity in fee-ſimple, for default of pay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment whereof after his death, (beſides th'annuity and ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rierages) I had a leaſe of a hundred yeres graunted me of certeine paſtures to the yearely valew of ſix pound by e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtimatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> for a pepercorne only I was co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tent, to th'end that the landes might be ſold for the ſatisfying of my brothers creditours, freely and for naught to releaſe my intereſt in that leaſe, which the law, for want of paiement of th'an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuitie, did euidently caſt vpon me: alſo to yeeld vp mine annuitie for the ſame ſumme of mony I had payed to my Brother, without both which my Brothers lande would haue found no conuenient ſale for the paiement of his creditors vntill this day. And of my dealing herein, I take witneſſe of Sir Robert Iermin of Suffolke, M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Atkins &amp; M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Tindall of Lincolnes Inne: who were (in deed) the men my brother truſted with his worldly eſtate: and who (in my iudgement) acquited the truſt my brother repo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed in them accordingly.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="accusation">
               <pb facs="tcp:19212:12"/>
               <head>M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> D. Sutcliffes <hi>accuſation.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>In his former booke he ſaieth, that I purchaſed three or fower good Mannours with the ſpoile of the Hoſpitall, and that only with the ſale of a cottage and three or fower Acres of land: or <hi>(as to my remembrance he ſpeaketh in another place of his former booke)</hi> as much land as would graze three or foure Goſelings. <hi>Looke alſo fol. 68. p, 2. of his later Booke, &amp; fol. 69.</hi> He may mend the matter if it pleaſe him, by conveying his landes and leaſes to his Hoſpitall: By which the law intendeth he hath gotte them for the most part. And fol. 70. He hath two leaſes at Welborne, he bought of <hi>M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lexander Morgan,</hi> yerely woorth two hundred markes: His landes in Norfolk<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> part wherof he had of his brother Stubbes, amount to halfe the ſumme: the valew of that he bought in <hi>Warwikeſhire</hi> he knoweth best him ſelfe, ſome benefite hee hath made of the leaſes of the Hoſpitall.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="answer">
               <head>Thomas Cartwrightes <hi>anſwere.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>Here is a charge of a purchaſe of three or foure good Mannors, and two good leaſes, &amp; both gott (for the moſt part) by <hi>the ſpoile of t'Hoſpitall,</hi> except the price of ſome ſmall <hi>Cottage, &amp;c.</hi> For the purchaſe of three or foure Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours, I neuer purchaſed any Mannour in my life but the Mannour of <hi>Saxmundeha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  </hi> in <hi>Suffolke,</hi> wherof I haue yet but he moitie, nether ſhal haue theſe fourtene or fiftene yeres, if one M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
                  <hi>Iohnſons</hi> leaſe be availeable, as hitherto he hath enioyed it by me: who haue not diſturbed his poſſeſſion. The rent that he yeeldeth for th'one half of the Demaines is but xxx. ſhillings by yeare. The rent of the demeines that I receiue (although enhanced as farre as the Tennant may liue thereof) is yet but xxvi. pound by yeare. Th'o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb facs="tcp:19212:13"/> rentes for Copieholdes come yearely to a iij. pound or thereabouts, as I remember. So that the whole of that I receiue cometh to litle aboue xxx. pound by the yeare. To purchaſe this I ſolde of the inheritance my Father &amp; grandfather left, as faire a houſe for a farme, not only as is in that towne where it ſtandeth, but in diuers townes a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout, which had betweene eight or nine ſkoare Acres of arrable land belonging vnto it, with commons, medow &amp; paſture agreable to the Farmes in that countrey, by yeere more then three times worth the valew that either my fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther or I receiued for it, &amp; yet we receiued betwene eight and nine pounds yearely of cleare rent diſcharged of all quitte rentes. That M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
                  <hi>Sutcliffe</hi> may the better enquire in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to it, the Farme is ſcituate in <hi>Waddon</hi> in the county of <hi>Cam<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>bridge,</hi> ſeauen miles from <hi>Cambridge,</hi> where I had alſo a coate with a cloſe adioyning vnto it, which I ſolde when I did ſell th'other. Now where hee ſaieth I <hi>purchaſed my landes with my Hoſpitall,</hi> I know not why he ſhould ſo often terme it my Hoſpitall, rather then (as it is truly called) the Hoſpitall of the Right honorable the Earle of <hi>Leiceſter:</hi> But this I know and profeſſe conſtantly, that neither I nor anie for me purchaſed one foote of lande ſince I came to the Hoſpitall: I ſoulde an annuitie in fee-ſimple of xii. pound x. ſhillings by yeare ſince I came thither, as my L. chief Iuſtice of her Maieſties como<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> pleas doth wel know, before whom I acknowledge a fine: Leaſes of the Hoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pitall I neuer made but one onely, for which the houſe &amp; not I receiued thirtie poundes. And becauſe he draweth me to theſe accoumptes of th'Hoſpital, I will offer, and in the hearing of any equall and indifferent Auditour will make it cleare, that beſides my continuall trauell for the ſetling and ſuites of the Hoſpitall, which I (neuer brought
<pb facs="tcp:19212:13"/> vp therevnto) would not haue vndertaken for anie mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney, but onely for conſcience and duetie to the poore Hoſpitall my L. truſted me with: I haue laied out of mine owne purſe fourty markes ouer and aboue that which I haue receiued or am like to receiue, vnleſſe the ſtocke which is holden from the houſe be recouered. This part<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie may appeare by an Accoumpt I gaue vp vnto her Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſties Comiſſioners who had charge (amongeſt others) to enquire and certifie the whole eſtate of the poore Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpitall. Now for the two Leaſes in <hi>Welborne,</hi> They were bought by a friend of mine, who beeing the principall dealer is left out, whether to draw more envie to me, let it be iudged, eſpecially of that which heereafter ſhall ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare: I confeſſe I ſhould haue had a part therin, but they were neuer enioied either of him or me, but were relea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
                  <hi>Morgan,</hi> for that he was not able without his vt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter vndooing, to performe them. And where hee ſaieth <hi>they were worth to me twoo hundred Markes by the yeare,</hi> They neuer haue bene nor will be woorth to vs both two hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred farthings in all: More then that (albeit my L. chief Iuſtice of England dealeth very honorably with vs) yet I referre it vnto his iudgement (if his Lordſhippe will be pleaſed to ſpeake in ſo priuate a matter) that we are great looſers by M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
                  <hi>Morgan.</hi> And M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
                  <hi>Morgan</hi> (if he haue but a ſparke of good nature) ſhall be conſtrained to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>feſſe our kinde &amp; chriſtian dealing with him, both in releaſing his bargaine for a ſumme farre vnderneath the valew it was woorth, and forbearing him many yeares with much pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tience, after the forfaiture of his Recognoiſance and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie promiſes broken with vs. Now where hee excuſeth theſe two laſt charges of being <hi>Executor to my Brother Stubbes, and of purchaſe of Lordſhips</hi> (as he doth excuſe many
<pb facs="tcp:19212:14"/> other things) in that he dooth propounde it onely in a queſtion, it is vnworthie of anie anſwere, not onely be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe a queſtion doth more ſtrongly ſometimes avowe, then a bare affirmation, but becauſe he is ſo violentlie &amp; bitterly caried againſt the petitioner for the thinges hee hath ſet down by way of queſtion. And for his excuſe of being miſtake<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> by the report of others, I referre it once a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine to iudgement, how it fitteth with the credite of a Miniſter of the Goſpell, to publiſhe (and that in print) what ſoeuer he receiueth by report, to the diſcredite of a Miniſter of the Goſpel, and vnleſſe M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
                  <hi>Sutcliffe</hi> will bring foorth his reporter, ſome will happily conceiue that it is the invention of his owne head. And if he did receiue it by report, yet ſeeing he would blow it abroad by ſo ſtro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g a blaſt, as is the print, at the leaſt he ſhould not haue ſim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply affirmed it, but ſet it downe as a report. Laſtly, where he ſaieth <hi>that he deſireth not to be acquainted with my eſtate,</hi> He forgetteth him ſelfe. For in his former booke (as I remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, for I haue not the booke at this preſent) he promiſeth to be a diligent Surveiour or Auditour of mine &amp; others mens Landes. And in deed he is ouer diligent that can finde Landes of mine in <hi>Warwikeſhire</hi> and <hi>Norfolke,</hi> wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of I my ſelf nor anie of my friendes know not one foote, yet M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> D. <hi>Sutcliffe</hi> admoniſhed in this behalf of his vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trueth ſet foorth in his former booke, and occaſioned thereby to correct him ſelfe, feareth not in this later to affirme boldely that if he haue done amiſſe, it is becauſe he hath ſet downe <hi>to litle, to much,</hi> (ſayeth he) <hi>I haue not ſet downe, fol. 69. pa. 2. fol. 70. p. 1.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="accusation">
               <pb facs="tcp:19212:14"/>
               <head>M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
                  <hi>D.</hi> Sutcliffes accuſation.</head>
               <p>Hauing good ſtore of money he hath good ſkill to make good vſe of it, <hi>M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Francis Michell</hi> ſhould haue payed him three hundred pound. And for the forbearing of it he receiued double vſance.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="answer">
               <head>Thomas Cartwrightes <hi>anſwere.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>What ſtoare of money I haue, I am not bound to giue M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
                  <hi>Sutcliffe</hi> accoumpt, what ſkill I haue to make vſe of it may partly appeare by the leaſes of M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
                  <hi>Morgan.</hi> And now it will further appeare by my dealing with M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
                  <hi>Francis Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chell,</hi> where firſt, as before he would make mee alone the owner of the two Leaſes, ſhutting out the principall dea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler, ſo heare for th'end before rehearſed, he maketh mee M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
                  <hi>Michells</hi> Creditor for three hundred pound, whereas the Recognoiſance he forfeited was to my friend &amp; not to me, and his principall debt was onely twoo hundred pound, and not three hundred pou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d. Now when the day of paiement approched, he came to me in the Fleete, and offered me intereſt to forbeare, which I vtterly refuſing, did notwithſtanding at his earneſt ſuite and complaint of his diſtreſſe yeeld to forbeare the debte. And gaue him a writing of my hand to this effecte, that I was for mine owne part content to forbeare him, with theſe conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, firſt that my graunt ſhould not bee hurtfull to my friend, not then in towne: and ſecondly, that it ſhould not be preiudiciall to the principall ſumme of two hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred pound. And where as he ſaieth in the Margen, that he will prooue this Intereſt by ſhewing the note of mine owne hand, let him ſhew the<note n="(a)" place="margin">Heere M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. Sutc. is put to the iumpe of a piece of his cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dite.</note> note and ſhame either me or him ſelfe; And if that be not ſufficient to cleare my
<pb facs="tcp:19212:15"/> righteouſnes in this cauſe, I appeale to his owne father M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
                  <hi>Mickiell,</hi> who was priuie to the whole courſe of our dealing with his ſonne. And we are ſo farre of from ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king Intereſt of him, that to this day beeing about fiue yeares at the leaſt ſince the money was due, we haue not receyued ſo much as the principall which wee onely de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded of him, although we had ſued out the forfeiture of his Recognoizance. And touching the matter of In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt, albeit I haue alwaies bene of iudgement for the lawfulnes of it, ſo it be with ſuch caution as Charitie (the rule of dealing with our neighbour) be not broken: yet in the time of my greateſt neceſſitie, when I was beyond the ſea, I receiuing aſſurance only for the bare money I left in the handes of my friends, did neuer couenant with them for the valew of one penie: But was content with what ſoeuer they them ſelues of their owne accord did alow, whether anie thing or nothing. Which dea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling alowed of thoſe which are the moſt bitter aduerſaries of Intereſt, M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
                  <hi>Sutcliffe</hi> may thinke with him ſelf how vntruly he dealeth with me in his ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſation of <hi>Double Vſance.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:19212:15"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
